A Guide to the Charlotte County (Va.) Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Books, 1806-1858
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Charlotte County (Va.) Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Books, 1806-1858
The Library of Virginia
1107377-1107382, 1107389-1107390, 1107393-1107395, 1107399, 1107406, 1107408, 1107417, 1107420, 1107429, 1107432, 1107439, 1107443, 1107445-1107447, 1107449-1107452, 1107455, 1107461, 1107504/Charlotte County (Va.) Reels 151-152
30 v. and 2 microfilm reels
Charlotte County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Charlotte County. These items were microfilmed by the Library of Virginia's Imaging Services Division.
Historical Information
Charlotte County was formed from Lunenburg County in 1764.
Scope and Content
Charlotte County (Va.) Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Books, 1806-1840, are rough drafts of personal property taxes compiled by the Commissioners of the Revenue. Some of the books have a listing at the front of the volume of the tax rates for that year. Information recorded for each person includes if applicable full name, number of white tithables, tithable slaves listed by name, number of tithable slaves older than 16 years of age, number of tithable slaves older than 12 years of age, numbers of horses and mules, and number of coaches, carriages and other taxable wheeled vehicles. There is no index.
Many of the memorandum books contain lists of free negroes and mulattoes following the tax information. Lists exist in the volumes for the years 1807, 1810, 1811 (2 volumes), 1817, 1820, 1821, 1822, 1823, 1824, 1825 (2 volumes), 1826, 1828, 1832, 1835, 1839, and 1840. Free negro lists give the full names of all free negroes in a particular household or family, numbers of males and females, and the occupation of the head of household.
Other books contain lists of alienations (transfers of property), lists of licenses, lists of voters, lists of militia enrollment, registers of births, and registers of deaths. Please consult the finding aid for additional information about which are included in which volume.
Lists of voters are recorded by voting district.
Lists of militia enrollment are given by voting district.
Licenses granted in the county in the 1856-1858 volumes record date of license, name of person or firm, business or professional license, name of sheriff to whom paid, standard by which amount of tax has been ascertained, amount of tax, amount of sales of ardent spirits, tax on sales of spirits, total amount of tax.
Registers of births record date of birth, name of child if named, white, colored (free/slave), sex (male/female), born (alive/dead), place of birth, father's name if free/owner's name if slave, father's occupation, father's residence, mother's name in full, how many in a birth, deformity or any other cause, source of information (name of person giving information; relation of informant).
Registers of deaths record name in full, white, colored (free/slave), name of owner of slave, sex (male/female), date of death, place of death, name of disease, age (month/week/day), name of parents, when born, occupation, consort of or unmarried, source of information (name of person giving information; designation of informant ie friend, physician, etc.).
Arrangement
Arranged more or less in alphabetical order by surname.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Charlotte County Commissioner of the Revenue and Free Negro and Slave records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Charlotte County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Free African Americans -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Land titles -- Registration and transfer -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Licenses -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Merchants -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Militia.; Slaveholders -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Slaves -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Tax collection -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.
Geographical Names:
Charlotte County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.
Genre and Form Terms:
Birth registers -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Death registers -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; First drafts -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Free negro and slave records -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Free negro lists -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Local government records -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Tax records -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.; Voters' lists -- Virginia -- Charlotte County.
Contents List
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1806
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1807
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 108
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1809
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1810
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 104
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1811
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 106
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1811
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes at the back of the unpaged volume.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1815
- Commissioner of the Revenue Record Book, 1815
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 140.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1817
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1817
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 113
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1818
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1820
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1821
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes at the end of the unpaged volume.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1822
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1823
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes at the end of the volume.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1824
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 132
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1825
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 119
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1825
  Includes list of alienations, pp. 130-137; and list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 139
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1826
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 127; and list of alienations pp. 130-133
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1827
  Includes list of alienations, p. 127
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1827
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 135
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1828
  Includes list of alienations in the back of the volume.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1828
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 143
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1830
  Includes on last page of unpaged volume a list of merchants' licenses.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1832
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 150
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1833
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1834
  Includes list of alienations at the back of the unpaged volume.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1835
  At the end of the unpaged volume there is a list of alienations and a list of merchants.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1835
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1839
- Commissioner of the Revenue Memorandum Book, 1840
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes, p. 145
- Commissioner of the Revenue Record Book, 1856
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes (1856), pp. 112-113; list of voters (1856), pp. 114-127; list of militia enrollment (1856), pp. 128-137; licenses granted in the county (1855-1857), pp. 138-141; register of births (1855), pp. 142-159; register of deaths (1855), pp. 160-169.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Record Book, 1857
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes (1857), pp. 113-114; list of voters (1857), pp. 115-128; list of militia enrollment (1857), pp. 129-138; licenses granted in the county (1856-1857), pp. 139-142; register of births (1856), pp. 143-162; register of deaths (1856), pp. 163-170.
- Commissioner of the Revenue Record Book, 1858
  Includes list of free negroes and mulattoes (1858), pp. 120-121; list of voters (1858), pp. 122-135; list of militia enrollment (1858), pp. 136-147; licenses granted in the county (1857-1858), pp. 148-151; register of births (1857), pp. 152-171; register of deaths (1857), pp. 172-180.